It was a good life
I feel I had a happy life
Sure, it had moments of regret
not having your own family
not having your own children
but that is how it happened
the cause was more important than the rest
and that is how life unfolded
so, my life was good
and I wish this life to many people
does one wish to have a long life?
I feel I've been living for a little too long
but yes, 96 years, you will cut this
sometimes you feel like you don't want to live
it is enough
but I still feel I will do something
those two tasks, I have to finish them
I simply cannnot surrender
I often have to force myself
but if you have an objective in life
that you have to accomplish
then you have a will to live and life is joyous
that's how I think it is
I was always Elizabeth (Elżbieta)
In France I was know as Elise Riviere
and as Elisabeth Brownet
I went all the way to Denmark
to Flensburg
In England I was never Elżbieta Zawacka
but always Elizabeth Watson
you see, so there I am Watson
and this attached itself to me,
I knew my own legend, who I was
as Elise Riviere or Kubica
I completely stopped being Elżbieta Zawacka
I was a courier from the very beginning
of the occupation
Consequently, I really know all kinds of tricks
for crossing the border.
I've made over 100 border crossings
so, I had to have my ways
that is your own sense
I knew which story to tell to each border guard
I was as fluent in German as I was in Polish
since I was born in Toruń
a city that was completely germanized
My father was a government official
if Polish was spoken in his family home
and police would report this
he would not be able to continue
as a government official
he would have a job
so, at home only German was spoken
if it became known
that any of the children spoke Polish
that would have been unacceptable
we had to speak German
when Pomerania was reunited with Poland
Arrival of (gen.) Haller, ceremonial arrival
which affected me so much emotionally
which affected my whole familly so strongly
arrival of Haller in Toruń
at that time I didn't speak Polish
so I had to attend a German school in Poland
since I didn't speak Polish
I remember my joy, when, having learned Polish,
I passed an exam to a Polish gymnasium
and I found out that I would be studying Latin
that was a dream come true,
'I would be studying Latin'
Funny, isn't it, my brothers studied Latin
I finished that Polish gymnasiusm
and I new right away I would study Mathematics
Prof. Krygowski was my academic advisor
when I was working on my Masters Thesis
Krygowski was this famous porfessor
at the university who had 3 assitants
Rejewski was already the senior assistant
of Krygowski
I was conducting my Mathematical exercises
and seminars with them
They were already involved in military service
working on cryptography needed by the army
They were already working for the army
We didn't know this
I know that the war would have lasted longer
if it wasn't for his Enigma
During my last year of university I've
experienced the most important event of my life
I joined military trainig for women
Since that time I had two services
to which I devoted my energies
It was my professional work as a teacher
and social work as an military instructor
responsible for combat training of women
It was called, in short, 'PWK'
We were preparing for military service,
as we knew that war was inevitable
I was involved in war preparations since
December 1930
Two years before the war
I took a leave from my teaching job
and I solely focused
on military preparation of women
as a commander of Silesia region
It was a large region, 19 counties
there was a need for trainig of all detachments
and so on
It was beautiful work
There were so many friendships which
you couldn't find anywhere else
because they were all so passionate,
participants of women's combat training
There were so many teachers,
fully devoted to service
I am asking myself a question:
'Was it worth all it?'
as the service was often very demanding
it would happen like that
But it's not enough to say 'It was worth it'
It gave us so much joy,
I lived so joyously during this service
My service in conspiracy, my military service
began on Krucza 12
I remember standing with Magda Zawodzińska,
Karasiówna joined us and
I repeat after her the words of the oath
I had a friend whom I initiated with the oath,
Teresa ???
After the war she told me that she included
the words of the oath in her daily prayer,
morning and evening
??? established a section, we called it the pan,
abroad
We had our own cells, I had one in Katowice
I called it 'the circus'
The one in Berlin, I called it 'Sabina'
Sabina was a co-worker of Jakubianiec
who worked for Poland in Japanese embassy
transferring reports to Sweden
that was one of our pen-cells
Here in Pomerania there was a cell
beautiful, 'Danusia'
which was transferring people to Sweden
It was made easier for me to create cells abroad
what was it?
It is very interesting.
Before the war I used to teach in Silesia
as a teacher of Mathematics
I used to teach in Tarnowskie Brzegi
Tarnowskie Głógi
There I functioned as a commander of PWK,
teacher of Mathematics
And there, near the public school was another school
called 'Lyceum of Raciborzanki'
It was a Polish school for polish girls,
daughter of Poles with German citizenship
And I, since I knew German equally as well as Polish,
and their Polish was not always up to par,
so the language was necessary
I was also teaching at the school of Raciborzanki
I would conduct discussion groups,
organize school trips, etc.
We became very close
All Raciborzanki girls lived along the Rhein,
in Berlin, other places
So, during the War I was able to use them
I would often go to Berlin in these matters
AK (Homeland Army) needed money
How do you deliver money from London?
It was done like this:
London would transfer money to a bank in Sweden
Swedish bank would transfer it to Berlin
and I would get it from Berlin for AK
So, there was a friendly, our, official,
naturally covert
who would take the money from the bank,
take it to doctor Ivo
I would arrive at his place,
he bought me a ...,
Well, we needed to transport it somehow,
it had to be cash, and cash takes a lot of space
It was a lot of money
I remember we bought a big suit case
from the war period, cheap one, not leather
and I would take it across the border
with that money
I never took the train directly to Warszawa
through Poznań, let's say,
Gestapo could have recognized me
if I was travelling too often
So, on the night train, during the curfew
I arrive in Sosnowiec
Come to the right address
My sister, Klara, lived there
I arrive, and, I would always give her a signal
by throwing a pebble at her window,
she lived on the second floor
the whole thing had to follow rules of consipracy
because I never knew whether I was being followed
I signal my arrival with a pebble, but nothing,
it is dark, she is not there, what is going on?
I am with this suit case
So I go to the second floor
The door to my sister's apartment doesn't open,
I go to the neighbour place, I knew her
The neighbour, pale as a ghost, mumbles
'what, you are here', and tries to close the door
I stuck my foot in the door and would let go
She said, just recently,
about 2 days ago Klara was arrested, my sister
I had a lot of acquanintances in Sosnowiec,
it was my area of operations from before the War
I go to Staszka Solikówna, I recall,
where I overnight with the suit case.
But, early in the morning around 5am
I get up and send her with the suit case,
what was I to do?
I told her to put it in storage
at the Post Office
The safest way, cheap suit case, for storage
She put it in storage
And what about me?
By the station in Sosnowiec goes a tram to Katowice
I jump on, in the last minute almost running
on to the tram to Katowice
But I notice that somebody else is jumping on
from the other side into the tram
So, I am being followed
I am in Katowice
In Katowice, near the Post Office we have our cell,
because we had to have cells
So I am going to ..., it was a cashier in
a pharmacy, I am going to the pharmacy
and loudly, in German, I ask for an aspirine
and I slip her the storage receipt from the Post Office
with that valuable suit case
I got rid of the receipt,
but I am still being followed
I can feel I didn't loose him
And now, to the train, to Kraków
I can feel that somebody is there, somebody else,
because they would switch, the same spy wouldn't
follow all the way
On that border I got sweaty, so horribly,
I was so scared, but he was quiet, let me go
He didn't arrest me at the border,
where it gets hard
I had good papers, of course,
I don't remember in whose name
and I arrive in Kraków
but I can feel sombody is there
because a person has that 7th sense
I can feel it,
so I need to loose him
I recall, walking around, it is almost afternoon,
I take off my coat, put it down,
wait a bit in this house a few minutes,
in another, I go into the store, finally
I go the train station
and there I wait, on Kraków train station,
good few hours,
I am waiting for the night train to Warszawa
But now I have to warn Warszawa
so I go onto the platform
I am looking for a way out,
how to escape those looks
I look,
and on the platform completely by happenstance
I see Maria Witek with an inspection in Kraków
completely by accident
I slip her a note 'I am jeopardized'
Now I could breathe a sigh of relief
I now new ..., Maria Witek from the underground
she will know what to do with it
Now I am calm,
I only know that I have to kill myself
nothing else,
because there is no other way
but, how does one kill oneself?
how do you do it?
Well, there is a simple way:
in Warszawa step out of the train,
jump in front of another running train,
and it will run me over
but I want to live,
I don't want to die
I want to evade those who are stalking me
jump out of the running train
I was affraid, I was affraid to jump out
The dawn is breaking,
we are approaching Żyrardów
I say, now is the only chance I can save myself,
I will jump out
Slowly, one step at the time,
in the doorway stands a Polish train conductor
I tell him: hold the door
He holds the door, I jump
The train stops soon afterwrards,
but I don't know if that's because
they noticed me jump or
is it stopping at a station
So I jump up, run to the forest nearby
I got to the forest,
'I am saved, I live'
Then I took a long road, I walked the whole day,
from Żyrardów, through the forest
in a round-about way all the way to Warszawa
I report to our contact, I am back from my assignment
When I mention the contact of the pharmacy cashier
in Katowice, that suitcase was so important that she
took it to Kraków personally
from there she sent a courier, they got the suitcase
with dollars and I am alive
They issued a warrant letter to trace me, I have
a number of this letter which contained my name and
place of birth, Elizabeth Zawacki, Toruń
And that's how they located my family, and they
arrested my whole family, besides Klara who was
in Sosnoweiec
They took my old father,
mother and my older sister
They arrested my brother, the one who latter perished
in Auschwitz
I could have, and Marcysia knew it, gone to Ciechanów
and attempt to rescue him.  They would have given me
the money, I suspect.
But it was almost certain they would have caught me
and arrest me and I, in turn,
could have broken down under investigation
At that time I already had very many addresses memorized
and I decided to give up on helping my brother
During the occupation, as my trips as a courier
were sporadic, I was able to study
I was studying in a free, covert Polish school
I was audting courses and in the meantime, every two
or three weeks apart I would make a trip
Polish Law did not give women the right to join
armed forces, they could only participate
as civilian aids
that was the reason for my mission to London:
to regulate women's military service,
to get those right for women
to tranform a civilian aid into a regular
soldier of the Polish Commonwealth
For four months I was studying courier paths to London
and parcels were huge, monthly, with a few hundred pages
on microfiche, with maps, graphs, our conspiracy worked so well
The had to dig up the archives after the War so I could
reconstruct the courier paths
from Warszawa through Germany, France, Southern France,
because it was separated by the border, Pirenees
and there, using my senses and without the help of our
network I crossed
It was very difficult, I report to (gen.) Sikorski
that (gen.) Grot is asking that I report to him
the state of communication in the country
and to return with his instructions
he listened but he realized I was going to return
to Poland, and normally the couriers did not return
and him, instead of listening to the report of
a humble soldier, who just arrived from the home country
of the hour of the meeting he was telling me
for 50 minutes that they are sabotaging
his efforts
and in reference to my report he said,
'when I come back, I have go to the East'
but he did not return from the East
he died in Gibraltar
'when I return I will listen to find out
of the state of communications'
He gave orders to the army in Poland,
but he didn't know about the situation in the country
and I must add, he didn't attempt to find out
about the situation
I came there straight from Poland, I could have
told them much, perhaps I didn't know how to tell it
but they showed no interest in the situation in Poland
They served Poland but they didn't
understand the situation
they lived their private lives,
drinking their coffees their breakfasts,
they had everything and we had nothing
it is a beautiful flight, but it is not me
approaching the ground,
the ground is approaching me
it is getting closer, and I jump,
I broke my heel, very painful
I was the first, after me one guy ended up
on a roof, the other a bit far,
but they found us
but just before landing I am yelling out
the password 'Janka', they recieve me
and, as usual, they want to hug me,
but they jump away, 'woman!'
that receiving party from AK that was below
well, they accepted 'that woman',
there I waited until the other landed
and got picked up
and then for 3/4 of an hour, with that hurting heel,
circling around the forest we've reached our cell
I returned right away to my work
in the underground, to the pen
I had to pass on the information
they didn't have in Poland
the whole thing was like this:
London co-operated with Warszawa,
Warszawa absolutely didn't know
that London was completely dependant
on the English
and expected too much from them
and London was not familiar with
our situation, and with their
unreasonable orders they impared our work
so I went to clarify it,
well, I tried to do it, but
it was almost the end of the war
11th of January '44 I was still on a trip to
Switzerland, I had a cell in Vienna called 'Waltz'
and I was comming from there and I wanted to
go to Warszawa, to report on my mission, as usual
I arrive in Sosnowiec where I find the front,
the Russians are already here
I wanted to get to demolished Warszawa
I recall comming from the train station,
because the train did reach demolished Warszawa,
only went as far as Szczęśliwice
I was walking by foot from Szczęśliwice
to Warszawa and I was singing
'This is the day of blood, this is the day...'
The Russians had such methods of corroding
the society, they had their spies everywhere
who reported
We regarded them as honest, decent Poles
but they were agents, and they spied
I didn't know who was betraying me
the commies organized manhunts,
great manhunts
they've been watching for a long time
there were those trials, those prisons
those horrible arrests of AK soldiers
it was like that
In Olsztyn, they arrested me in 1951,
that's when everything ended
I was imprisoned,
naturally, they spared no death threats
since I was a former AK member
I ended up getting 10 years,
the sentence of 10 years
later those 10 years got shortened to 4
and was released during the period of 'the thaw'
Even this UB prison, however many years,
nothing, it was not important
it was important to be able to do something
I wanted to be a reasercher
and I managed
thought it took a while after my prison term
until I've put everything back together
One time they destroyed all my research materials
But I finished my doctorate in '65
and all my time I was involved in research
this filled my days
I had a rare specialization:
adult education
In particular, I wanted to start an
open University, similar to the one
in Great Britan
and I was preparing professorship
selection commitee was in session
A big Institue of Education at University
created to remove me, did not create
the department of Andagogy
and then I could retire, and I retired
then I got involved in intense work,
let's call it, service dedicated to memory
of the fate of the nation
because all togehter it is
the life of the nation
in which each of us played our tiny part
that we had to rediscover, this underground service
we immediately needed to establish archives
of AK in Pomerania region
and it happened,
but this is just one section: Pomerania
in addition, we were looking
for information about women of Pomerania
and then we widened our scope,
then we created an archive dedicated
to women in war service
all fighting women
civilian and uniformed
in the East and in the West
I was collecting, we are trying to
put together this Museum
and the third archive is my beloved,
it is an archive of a single detachment
of Polish Underground
communication between Warszawa and London
when I am approaching 100 (years of age)
I have one task, actually two tasks ahead of me
which I have to complete
the first to finish publishing of the
dictionary of women decorated with
cross Virituti Militari
I am always concerned that
I will run out of time
before I finish what I started
and the last task of my life is
to make sure that Warszawa gets a
monument commemorating this great accomplishment of women
involvment of women, half of the nation,
in saving of the nation
I don't like this word 'hero', because
that is not what I am interested in
because a heroic act is singular,
even if it is a great effort/sacrifice
but it is about continuous service,
this complete devotion, sacrifice of your family,
everything for the service
Poland is raising new generations,
Poland, when rich culturally,
is better prepared to form new generations
it is rich, and that is this flow of history
it is necessary that the culture is
being enriched continously
so the next generation can access as much
as possible, and not loose out because
there is no record of the past
I feel that those experiences need
to be passed on
the nation cannot loose a single generation
your generation also has to find its place in history