the law and the fist
From corners of the earth
from rowan sheltered ways
where cindered forest, wind exhausted
night and front
where wasted harvest fell
where hawthorn turned to black
day awakes
The Sun will embrace us with its hands
and look earth has swollen with blood
once more will bear us a fief of grain
golden dust
Women will take us into thier huts
and look at them laugh through their tears
once more a dance tune will ring out loud
maybe here
Next day, or two, a night or three
though not today
Bread will the ovens bake for us
and look where smoke vailed everything
Flower will bloom in that war scared mark
deep rose tint
New children will be born to us
and look, they are laughing that we
still are rehashing that wretched time
spell of storms
Next day, or two, a night or three
though not today
Nights pass, day's gone
one day new dawn
shall wake again
HELP, PEOPLE, HELP, HELP ...
HELP, HELP, HELP, ...
STAND DOWN !!!
Leave him alone, what's going on
Little misunderstanding
Little or big?
medium
Disperse, right now!
One against three
How unfortunate
Damn
Did you see that girl?
Which girl?
The one with the braid, stood here, dissappeared
I don't know anything, sir,
girls don't concern me
Oh, tobacco, not bad, aromatic
Would you know if there are
any forests in the area?
No I don't, I am not from around here
Your train took off
Do you now when the next one will come?
Maybe in an hour, or three days,
are you in a hurry?
No, I am not
Do you have any work around here?
Come with us, we could use a cowboy like you
... and pants
what?
pants, will you give me a pair
well, not right away
I need them
new pants
Besides, I am looking for something ... more quiet
Go and see the supervisor
over there, in the castle behind the river
Good Day
Do you know this building?
a bit
I am looking for the supervisor
what for?
professional secret
professional secret?
Well, let's go
Please ...
It is you
What is this professional secret?
regarding work
Aha, your profession?
I studied Education.
Write down your last name, ... first
from the camp?
can't hide it
You are the first teacher
You realize that we need to
start organizing everything from the start
I don't want to teach
Why not?
I can't, I am not fit for it.
So, what do you want to do?
I want to be a forest ranger
A forest ranger
Come back in a week
In a week I will be somewhere else
Could you ration me a pair of pants?
Will you help us organize our Education?
no
And a sense of duty, things like that, nothing?
Good Bye
hey, hallo
Which camp were you in?
in Auschwitz, ... and later in Dachau
I was in Pawiak, Majdanek, Buchenwald, Mauthausen, Oranienburg
You were in Mauthausen also
that's right, that's right
Czesiek
Andrzej
What will you do now?
I don't know
Can you drive?
I can
C'mon, I will set it up for you, c'mon, c'mon
Thank you Doctor
these documents will suffice
Here is your letter of authority
There are all kinds of people around here,
trust is most important
We need specialists, people of courage,
but most importantly honest ones
Doctor
he can drive
maybe there is a spot for him with our group
I have a feeling that this man
is only concerned with material matters
But for us, we are looking for something more
but I don't want anything more
only to make some money?
only
a lot?
as much as I can
I am affraid we will be leaving without this man
but Doctor, he can be of use
What is your name?
Andrzej Kenig
Volksdeutsche (German Collaborator)?
no Way, he is our boy,
he was in the Auschwitz and Dachau
Do you have any documents?
No, I don't
anything
I don't have anything
So, how can I trust you?
I am giving you my word of honor
ahhh, ...
I think Mr. Kenig can go (with the rest of you)
Lieutenant
Graustadt, in polish Siwowo
Small town located off the main highway,
no telephone service
The population was probably evacuated
by retreating german troops
You are an operational group
that must secure the town for repatriates
organize the government, activate health services
The matter is urgent, Gentlemen
They are sending us wounded for recovery
We need to put full effort into it
Well, the task is dangerous
there might be left over german troops in the forest
Please sign the requisition order
Gun cases are over there,
choose for yourselves
Mielecki
Wijas
Wróbel
Smól, ... Smólka
Smółka
Smółka?
Antoni
Rudłowski
Kenig, ... please
Weapons to be used only
when absolutely neccessary
and in self-defense
give it to me,
I will help you
What is it, broken?
no, sir, most likely an infection
no, sir, most likely gangrene
he's got a little scratch
Thank you very much,
I am Rozłowski
Kenig
Mister Supervisor,
let us begin with execution of our tasks
one moment Gentlemen
maybe they are poisoned
the germans used to poison drinks before leaving
I will drink your portion
Gentlemen, I wish you a few pairs of pants
and material benefits, within reason
for me, maybe a shirt, size 38
Most importantly
to re-activate health facilities
and to secure public property
Best Wishes, Gentlemen
I drink to the success of our cause
and you in a round-up? (caught by the Nazis)
no, during the uprising
to Kacet (Concentration Camp)?
I was lucky as it was
they would usually blow our guys down
I didn't make it across Wisła
to Kacet (Concentration Camp)?
Most importantly, brother, it is to be alive
when I got back we broke 5 liters
And how was it for you?
Building reduced to powder
I started to dig
destroyed my pants
What for anyway?
let them lay there
Could we swap places?
Why?
It is windy over here and I am very sensitive
Do you want some, Aspirine, Bayer's original
No
Thank you
Our kidneys, Mr. Kenig, are in tripple danger:
shaking, wind and dust
You can get off, you will be 'healthy like a bull'
It is said that soul is immortal
and body is nothing
dust, ... wasted waste
God helps those who help themselves
What if there are no vehicles there?
They have to be there,
they used to leave them everywhere
they've been without gasoline lately
Holly cow, not a soul
Damn, where did they come from
Well, why aren't you saying anything?
Poles?
kind of
What are you doing here?
We came here for a little spring picnic
And what is this, a bit of loot?
A few rags, we got the from the americans
We've heard it is a great place
Why great?
Kościuszko overnighted here?
Hitler's lover
and she left a lot of underwear
I want to find a nice dress
That won't work my ladies
I am very sorry
but we are here to protect public property
Turn around, now...now...now...now
Boss, let's take these girls
Why?
Just for fun
Without girls, it will be lame, why suffer?
Boss
Six of us, four of them, what do you think?
What does that have to do with anything?
Hey, ... you can stay
but we will have some fun, agreed?
Fantastic, last time I danced
was at a ball in Petersburg
But I have to stress that in my group
army discipline is required, absolute obedience
I think we can make that promise
Good stuff, we did great, holy shit
Keep your mouth shut, women are present
Not to worry Director, I have a colorful resume
I will throw one more
Leave it
Drop it
and I don't want to see it again
We came here to secure this place,
not to break windows
understand?
Yes sir, Doctor
Hitler
Where?
Over there, behind the window
Comb the city, women must hide
I am not hiding, I am going with you
Me too
Kenig to movie theater, Rozłowski over there
Smółka, Czesiek this way
Wijas
Please wait here
careful
He is alive
Wounded?
Drunk as a skunk
We found a German
Drunk beast
You, ... you, get up
Open your eyes
Can you see us
Wretched sun, wretched dream
We are Polish
Good Day Ladies and Gentlemen,
I am Schaeffer
Reservations and service supervision
at hotel Tivoli
Please forgive my appearance
Did you operate the radio?
That is possible
Are we gonna wack'em?
Will you do it?
The town was empty and it should remain empty
Take him to the hotel
Get up, ... GET UP!!!
To the hotel
Well Kenig,
you can look for some pants for yourself
And you ladies can also look for some clothing
I don't know why, but I get the impression
that I have seen you somewhere
I do appologize
Are you from Warszawa?
No
Then it was just an impression
Most certainly
Would consider living in the forest?
No
Why not?
I'd be affraid
I wanted to spread the rugs on the floor
but I didn't have time
Hard to do anything
when you have too much time
Why did you stay behind?
I don't know, I got drunk
What were you during your stay here?
Nothing big
I drank, opened doors, I opened almost all of them
Please allow yourself ...
Are there any trucks in town?
Trucks?
Listen, I am the new mayor here,
Understood?
Yes sir
I am very pleased to meet you Mister Mayor
There are trucks
Here, the keys to the cellar at Tivoli
Best supplied cellar in Graustadt
I am sleeping, not a worry in the world,
I am sleeping
Take a look
Maybe you will find something for yourself
Did you find anything?
Broad with no taste,
her waist had to be three times my size
You can take a look at this 'broad with no taste'
September last year,
they were just finishing us off in Warszawa
Looks like her daughter
was similar to you in size
You need to look in the other room
Just look at it, this is serious money
Doctor Mielecki
Yes
Doctor, I am reporting to Zielno through sanitary transport
The Supervisor is asking for a quick report
about the condtion of the health facilities
and that of the town
Ah, and Doctor, repatriates are waiting
Thank you, Thank you
everything will be taken care of
And when are you returning?
Ah, no, no, no, the Supervisor asks
that I remain here with you, sir
That's great, great, you will organize
a police station here for us, right?
Will do
Well, take a room and wash yourself
It wasn't easy getting here,
I barely found a way
Everybody hid somewhere,
I was worried that something happened to you
the truck is just sitting there, nobody around
This town is great, ... yes
it is nice here
people will have ...
What did you do with yourself?
I tried to comb my hair
You look nice in this sweater
Really?
Do you not feel some kind of distaste,
... scrupuls?
scrupuls?
Because they turned me into a beggar?
Because they took away my husband?
Tourtured, and when I was half-dead
filled my mouth with gypsium
To hell with all of their posessions
To hell with them all
It's funny
What?
Everything
Princely establishment
for nouveau riche store owners
I used to visit such establishments
at five in the morning, when I stopped caring
about the decor
Ladies, you did not forget about the our evening?
Of course not, we will be dressed to kill
Drug stores here are well supplied
We have trucks, but only three are functional
Oh, that's a measly find
but they have trailers
Mr. Kenig, please join us
Gentlemen, we are in better shape than I expected
We drink to the success of our cause,
... to our success
Gentlemen, time to secure the property,
bring everything of higher value to the hotel
Kenig and Smółka will inspect the shoe stores
you, photoshops and optical,
and then, in turn, the rest
Old icon, where did you find it?
In the cellar
Where there more?
They are there, really dark in there
only icons?
no, lots of pictures, but disgusting,
naked bodies together with figures of saints
Sin
and books
old?
written ...
... by hand
yeah
let's go
but, ... the shoe stores
ahh, enough time
Museum collection
What?
Museum (stuff)
whatever, I am starved
me too
what is it today, Friday?
I don't know, I don't think so
that's good,
they will cook some canned meat for us
it's all ours
no kidding
I mean, Polish
Library in Kórnik, Warszawa
Expensive?
for sure
what is this?
illustrated script from middle ages
Expensive?
like hell
How much?
There is no price
half a million, a million?
There is no price!!!
a million I figure
Let me see.
And this little picture, worth a lot?
Quite a bit
So, take it
take the picture and will take these scribbles
Leave it
Why?
property of the nation
the nation won't suffer (from its loss)
LEAVE IT !!!
Give it to me
Doctor would finish you off
and I will just beat the crap out of you
Put it away
inside, or it will get damaged
What's up, ... in a hurry to meet your maker
I will tell, ... I will tell Boss
Gimme a smoke
You were fighting, ... like you give a damn
Weak, ... I am still weak
Where is that damn book?
Darn, it is dark
Smółka, ... it is said 'thou shalt not steal'
So, why did you come here?
To earn some money
Well,  trucks if there are documents
and you are set for years
What does the Doctor want to take from here?
Whatever he can
Hospital Equipment?
Everything
And those who will come here
repatriots, wounded,
what will happen with them
Just wait, you will be condemned
We are not stealing
This belongs to no one
God will remember
who resisted and who followed the voice of evil
Boss will rub you out
I am not alone
Who else is with you?
You are
I am?
And who else?
Czesiek
Where is my hat?
Boss promissed to get me an absolution
Smółka
Nah, I have to ask Boss
You won't tell him anything
Damnation, ... dark
... two bottles
I feel it
Who says I do not feel it
Head's buzzing, vaporizing
World's turning like a housefly
Whiskey, who says we don't drink Whiskey
And now you drunken mugs
What will be drinking next
Rum
Rum, we'll drink by glasses rum
For even bigger buzz, for even louder noise
Rum, we'll be drinking damned rum
Till dawn, till sleep will take its hold, that deadly chum
Cognac, so how about some Cognac,
That temple smashing hammer,
true aromatic gold
golden, so what that it is golden
when blood simmers from longing
earth has enough of gold
Wine, rivers flowing with wine
Children, let them drink wine,
wine only gets you down
Gin we will drink, murderous gin
hang ups leave with a spin
let it torch devil's heir
silly story
Gin we will drink, murderous gin
...
Why are you laughing?
(smiling) to you
There is one and one only
whom I love the most
I will give all for her
all my days and my nights
I know how to love,
truly, fervently and gently
passionately, willingly and madly
...
... I know how to love,
quitetly ...
Not a single clean glass
Alcohol disinfects
Can you take a good look at her, will you
sure
I have it hooked up with her
congrats
By any chance, would you know
if cibazol works preventively
I don't know, why not ask the doctor
He is a Doctor the way I am a Minister
How so, what about the documents?
Documents, ... maybe you need some?
Doctor, ...
Quiet
I have a proposition
What is it?
Lots to talk about
Quit wrecking the mood, brother, leave it
You are scared
You drank too much
Yeah, yeah
Where is the post office?
On the Post street
Go to the square and turn right
then take the first left
Listen, occupy Smółka with a conversation, ok?
I will be right back
I won't drink vodka, no
Will you have a drink with me?
I can have a drink
What is your name?
..., I know, I know, Hanka
I've been watching you since the morning
I won't be like that, I will respect you
You won't be unhappy with me
we will have a farm, money,
you will buy anything you want
Money is of no interest to me
Andrzej told you this
heavenly kingdom, he says,
will belong to the poor
And where is our professor?
Where is Mr. Kenig?
Probably went to bed
Oh, alone?
Mister Mayor
Are you asking about Mr. Kenig?
Yes
Professor went to the Post Office
What?
Czesiek
Czesiek !!!
Kenig went to the Post Office
Hallo, ... hallo
Yes, hallo
Hallo, Zielno?
No, Korzów, where did you connect from?
go on ... go on, hallo
Could I speak with the Supervisor in Zielno?
Unfortunately no,
maybe you want to connect with Poznań
or Warszawa, I have those lines open
Hallo, can you hear me, hallo
Connect me with police in Gorzów
Are you a criminal?
Yes, and will start shooting
if you don't connect me immediately
I will try, rigth away
Hallo
Hallo !!!
Yes, can you hear it, no one is responding
they maybe on patrol, apparently something happened
Sure you don't want to connect with Warszawa?
Some other time,
now please listen to me carefully
Yes
You must inform the Supervisor
or police in Zielno, that Kenig was calling
Kenig
Yes, Kenig from Siwowo
The town is in good shape,
but they must send people with machine guns
Yes
Did you understand me?
I understood, are you in danger?, ... hallo
Hallo
Are you in danger?
I don't know, oh, one more thing,
nobody knows about this call,
Good Night
Talk, ... you see, nobody here
The kraut bullshited
There is signal, damn
We gotta have the whole thing ...
What is this foolin' around?
I am practicing
I am shooting the bottles
Easy, quit those stupid pranks
Were you at the Post Office?
at the Post Office, what for?
man, can you shoot, holly cow,
where did you learn it?
in the resistance
what were you doing there
where?
in the resistance
everything
and discipline, didn't they theach you there
I beg your pardon, but I do not understand
I will explain it to you
You see
without talented people, we can even get by
We only need those who are obedient
and how much am I going to get for it
for what?
let's say, for being obedient
enough for a pair of pants
I am affraid you underestimate me
ten percent, Kenig, hmm?
of the whole thing
Will we have to run away abroad?
not out of the question
now I am beginnig to worry
that you overestimate me
I want to earn as much as I can
because I don't have anything
but on the way here I didn't expect
we would get this far
Doctor, ... I've grown to like this place
I would like to stay here
forever?
you make a career
Doctor
will you give me a bit of time to think
whole night ahead of us
Where are you now?
What kind of slave you ...
... east has some kind of connection
with the proponents of metapsychosis
telepathy and reincarnation of souls
anyway, a there was a similar case in Kraków
I remember one of the professors invited us ...
don't cry, don't cry, don't cry, DON'T CRY !!!
leave me alone
Where is Anna?
I dunno, she doesn't want me
why?
you snitch
What are you doing here?
I ran away from Smółka
wants to get married
promisses a farm and respect, he's very nice
you know it's funny
but in the camp,
sometimes when I used to think about freedom
my dreams would hover around something like that
I didn't dare to expect anything
he will tell him now
what?
Andrzej, what is going on here?
well, make it short
Boss, those medical contraptions,
we shouldn't be taking them
Who told you this?
nobody, I by myself
Kenig, eh?
Not Kenig, what does he understand?
he just wants to earn a lot
you didn't figure it out by yourself !!!
what, do you think that I am nothing
I also have my own mind
NO !!!
exagerration
Doctor, ... sin, ... this is for the wounded
Smółka, don't rack your brains over this
it is not for you
Listen only to me, you will be better off
You will have money, you will build a house
you will buy a pair of horses, cows, plow
motor bike
and a motor bike, you will live
you will live, like a count
no, those contraptions must not be taken
buddy, go to bed, you are drunk
THOSE CONTRAPTIONS MUST NOT BE TAKEN !!!
It is said 'thou shalt not steal', right?
you are right
but it is also said 'thou shalt not kill'
yes
and, what have you got there?
a pistol
for killing?
... must not be taken ...
ok, ok, ok, buddy, go to your room,
get some sleep
I can't, I can't
and it was going to be such a joyous evening
where did they go, all those wonderful men
where is my neighbourhood, where is that street?
where is that house?
you always carry on about this Petersburg
I've never been there
I am Dubikowska from the Lublin area
with my husband,
we danced away a few beautiful farms
didn't work out, no keys to the car
and other vehicles are without gas
careful
we are posting guards,
Czesiek
you will guard the hall till 3:00am
then wake up Wijas
the last one on duty Rudłowski
and what about Smółka, he is a Saint?
drunk, he is sleeping
are you excluding me?
I don't wish to deprive Ms. Anna of your company
Just in case, it is safer to not leave the hotel, please
I wish you, ladies and gentlemen, a good night
I found a stamp collection, should we take a look?
in bed?
What is your room number?
wait there
we wanted to look at the moon
what's so interesting about it
that it's so pale
surely from fear
I congratulate the young couple
you are very nice, although silent
you have no idea what a chore it is
to listen to all of that
enjoy yourselves
Janka
will you do something for me?
for you anything
you must somehow get out of here,
but please continue smiling at me, ok
you will go to the Post Office right from the square,
then the first cross street to the left
and then
from there you will make a phone call to wherever,
and, in my name, request that they send police
phone office is on the second floor
but we are the only two who know about it
Can't you make up your mind?
I've sent Janka to the Post Office
maybe she will make a connection
go to your room
I will try to get through to Czesiek
Andrzej
leave them
when are we leaving?
at the break of dawn
I am not going
I want to stay here
What are you expecting here?
normal life
here?
yes, here
and that's why I won't let anyone
take anything from here
who are you saying this to, eh?
to you
because I am expecting you will help me
what planet did you fall from,
you idiot
for 3 years in the camp I was eating turnips
I told myself, once it is over, if I survive
I will be somebody, you understand?
now I have the right to take everything
from whom?
tomorrow will arrive bunch of beggars like you and I
at least they should get what is here
I did my thinking about the fatherland during the war
now I am thinking about myself
I want to have money, a house, a woman
I would like to fall in love
and you donkey, walk in your ragged pants
and quit stirring the pot or you might get it
I will get it
Where were you tramping around?
Eh, watch your language, mister handsome
and keep your hands to yourself
you lock me out and then throw an argument
go to sleep
with pleasure, Good Night
someone must have been there, phone is broken
Mister, how do you do it?
I promise marriage
I know everything
Yes, I know everything
I will tell you how to take women
Mister, without a sentiment
if you sprinkle more you get more,
you sprinke less then, well, you know
You gotta have something to sprinkle
You think that a girl did a number on me?
Never
I could also roll like you
meander like a romantic, that poet Mickiewicz
But what for?
Why do you wear gloves?
eh ..., I have, you see, ugly hands, and ...
Good Night, sir
Good Night
It looks like I am on my own
I expected that
What will you do?
I don't know
I beg you leave it all
What time is it?
almost break of dawn
I am affraid that police doesn't know
anything about us
You did all you could
clearly, you won't stop them all by yourself
I don't know
Andrzej
I am affraid
Can't you understand that?
I am hoping I will manage somehow
AND I DON'T WANT THAT!!!
I don't want that, understand?
I was thinking I would regain my peace
Can't you see what they turned me into?
I am affraid
I've been affraid for six years,
everyday
I despise those macho faces of yours,
those guns of yours, all this heroism
That's why I need to purge this trash,
to regain peace
I also have to learn to believe
that one can live honestly
Anna
leave me
I am not a snitch, professor
Mayor is Mayor, we need to obey authorities
Mielecki is no Mayor
Understand? !!!
Oh my dear God
Anna?
Are you angry with me?
They are leaving
and you?
I am staying
Where are you going?
get something to eat
Professor
I am hungry
Professor, I would like to show you something
You are drunk again
I am not drunk, follow me
get ready girls, we are leaving soon
What am I supposed to do with it, Professor
Andrzej
Andrzej !!!
Antek, ... Smółka, ... SMÓŁKA !!!
It had to hurt
punctured lungs
This is horrible, let's get out of here
Who did this?
I don't know, I don't know anything,
I was sleeping all that time
They are bandits, we have to stop them
but why me?
so you can look at your face in the mirror
they will kill us, I don't want to
I don't know anything, I don't know any...
You won't let them get away with it, right,
you will arrest them, call the police
Doctor
I agree to the terms, I am coming with you
Right, I understand it
come down
What is the meaning of this, Doctor,
apparently you don't wont to take us with you
Unfortunately, dear lady, the contract has expired,
this is where we part ways, Good Bye
but ...
Which truck?
this one
Rudłowski with me
ok
Get in
And you?
What about me?
Which truck are you taking?
Opel
Good Bye, ... beauties
Mielecki, step away from the trucks
Step away from the trucks
Hide, God dam'it !!!
right now, to the hotel
Drop your weapon, ... surrender
Raise your hands and approach the hotel
Andrzej Kenig, surrender, otherwise you'll die
We are offering your survival and money
Andrzej Kenig, ... surrender,
... raise your hands and approach the hotel
Andrzej Kenig,
We are offering your survival and money
Drop your weapon and approach the hotel
Andrzej Kenig, surrender
Drop your weapon, surrender,
we are offering your survival and money,
you will die otherwise, Andrzej Kenig
Drop your weapon
Don't shoot, ... no, no
Why did you shoot, what for?
I was affraid
Rudłowski can you see me?
Rudłowski !!!
Block the streets
Enough shooting, go away, leave the town,
you hear me, enough shooting
And was it all worth it, Kenig?
I told you, without talented people we can get by
we only need obedient ones
Mielecki is dead, don't shoot
don't shoot, Mielecki is dead
shoot !!!
oh you, ... you rag, ... coward, ... ah you
give me the machine gun
give me the machine gun !!!
I was protecting myself
man, can you shoot
let's go
get in !!!
get in the trailer
What do you want?
Unload the truck, immediately
shoot
Gestapo didn't kill me, then you finish me off
You murderer
That's what I survived the camp for
You can kill me you bastard
you flea bag
piece of shit
God Damn, we got your message too late
But I see you've managed
You've accomplished a great feat
I killed, ... three
In self-defense
I am not sure
Defending public property
Supervisor wants you to become ... a Mayor here
I have to leave this place
where?
I have to leave
Give him a ride
Yes sir
The Sun will embrace us with its hands
and look earth has swollen with blood
once more will bear us a fief of grain
golden dust
New children will be born to us
and look, they are laughing that we
still are rehashing that wretched time,
spell of storms
Next day, or two, a night or three,
though not today
1:31:32,800 --+ 01:33,400 >>> color#00FF00;I;B;size:12px
Night pass, day's gone
one day new dawn
shall wake again
THE END